Alexey Bochkarev

Researcher in Mathematical Optimization / Operations Research PhD candidate, Clemson University

Research interests and experience

Combinatorial optimization, decision diagrams and graphs, network optimization and interdiction. Current project aims to apply game playing and reinforcement learning techniques to the Dynamic Shortest-path Interdiction problem. Previous one dealt with the Consistent Path Problem, trying to get computational edge in combinatorial problems by representing binary constraints (e.g., in a variant of the Facility Location problem) as Binary Decision Diagrams. **Research supervisor:** Dr. J. Cole Smith.

A. Bochkarev, J.C. Smith, On Aligning Non-Order-Associated Binary Decision Diagrams, revision submitted to *INFORMS Journal on Computing*. Results presented at INFORMS Annual conference, 2020.

Education

PhD Industrial Engineering (2018–2021 exp) Clemson University, US. OR track

MSc/BSc Appl. Math and Physics (2004–2010) Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology, Russia

M.A. Economics (2008–2010) New Economic School, Russia

Selected coursework

University: Mathematical Programming, Network Flows, Algorithms and Data Structures, Stochastic Programming intro, Power Markets and Regulations, Game Theory, Probability / Statistics, Foundations of Data Science, Calculus & Co.

Online: Analytics Edge (MITx @ EdX), ML basics (Andrew Ng @ Coursera).

Programming skills

Main stack: Python (gurobipy / gurobi, pulp/cbc, numpy, pandas, matplotlib/plotly/seaborn), R (ggplot, dplyr, tidyverse), C++, Julia (JuMP)

Basic knowledge: PyTorch, Java, Matlab/Octave

Other technical skills

PBS (comp cluster), GNU/Linux, bash; make, git, LATEX, Emacs, basic GIS (QGIS), Inkscape, beamer / PPT / LO Impress / reveal.js, Jupyter Notebook.

(Human) Languages

English (fluent), Russian (native), German (A1).

Teaching experience

Designed and delivered two 4-days mini-courses for gifted high-school students and early undergrads: "Practical Intro to Probability" and "A Glimplse into Algorithms", 2021 (RUS, ENG).

TA in "Intro probability" course, ENG, CU, 2021

Other initiatives: "OR Tech Seminar" (research toolbox, 4 workshops, 2021)

Service & Community

INFORMS Chapter: Secretary (2020), President (2021); "Journal club on Network optimization and interdiction" (2021)

SMTB, ZPSH: summer/winter schools for high-school students, instructor (2020, 2021)

Industry experience

The Federal Grid (FGC UES) (2013–2017)

Electricity transmission, Moscow, Russia

Role: Team head: modeling and analytics

Focus: Performance benchmarking (branches), operational efficiency improvement. Internal regulations/KPI, strategy, analytics, and presentations.

Ministry of Energy of Russia (2013)

Public service: energy (electricity), Moscow, Russia

Role: Deputy team head

Focus: Transmission & distribution grids, benchmarking, economic efficiency. Analytics, presentations.

Roland Berger Strategy Consultants (2010–2013) Strategic consulting, Moscow, Russia

Role: Intern \rightarrow Junior Consultant \rightarrow Consultant Focus: Infrastructure and construction. Strategy and performance: market entry, supply/demand modeling, growth strategy, efficiency improvement.